push to not feel fear slashnot feel the
ego quote unquote slash etc can be
dangerous not because the lesson is
false though it may be but because of
the social pressure around those words
in fact there's a universally frowned
upon quality called being egotistical
ego is embedded in it and also to be
seen as retreating is the same as being
seen as being defensive which is the
same as being fearful which is seen as
being lower on the spiritual hierarchy
perhaps it's true that you should feel
less disquitude about certain facts
though perhaps your disquitude is
justified for where you are now. And
that's okay. It's 100% okay. It took me
about 1 year to realize that. In fact,
perhaps more than one year. It took me
over one year to realize that these
spiritual lessons tend to not have the
physics notion of path dependence.
Perhaps you shouldn't uncritically adopt
an eastern practice in a western world
and vice versa. Or perhaps certain
truths are dependent on the path that is
where you are now rather than being
independent of anything. Frankly, it's
embarrassing to reveal myself as so
selfish and malicious and cowardly, and
to do so so unguardedly to Carl Fristen
and even to you,
as I'm a as I'm a relatively thin-kinned
person, at least currently I am. But
hopefully in the end, it's a net
benefit. The dangers of going on to
journeys of investigations into
consciousness, the self, computational
reality, and even the phenomenon, as it
can lead to a spiral down some viciously
dark paths that are at least ostensibly
irrevocable while having certainty that
your newfounded conception of reality is
indeed truthful. While I don't like to
state personal opinions because I
generally don't have many strong views
and the views that I do have are fickle,
changing week by week sometimes. My
current conclusion is that if it's not
lifeaffirming, if it's not loving, if
it's not something you can tell others
without others being horrified and
frightened for you, then use that as a
sign that what you're experiencing or
what you're feeling or what you think is
not truthful. Please seek help. Don't
suffer alone. You're not alone. And you
can verify that simply by talking to as
many people as you can. If you're
listening to this podcast, then it's
likely because you at least have some
trust in it. So trust that statement or
at least test that statement out. Now on
to the guest. Carl Fristen is a
professor of neuroscience at University
College London and is one of the most
cited individuals in his field. He's
also the inventor of the free energy
principle and is someone who's made
advances in the field of active
inference that's matched almost by no
one. He may be one of the most
insightful and brilliant people on the
planet. I've been lucky enough to speak
to Carl before in a substantive 4-hour
podcast linked below, which is best
watched at least twice to properly
understand. This episode is an outlier
in the tow channel because this will
serve as an introduction to that episode
as many after watching that were still
unclear as to what the free energy
principle is. If you feel like you're
lost, that's okay. Let that be a theme.
Understanding is less like a light
switch and more like a stove top. That
is it's not like all of a sudden you
have an insight and then you understand
some phenomenon. You went from 0 to one.
It's more like you get a gradual
increase in understanding where a
modicum here makes more sense and then a
smidg in here. As Wheeler says and I
like to quote the point isn't to drink
from the fire hose but instead to get
wet trusting that your conscious
befulement is part of the process and
unconsciously more is becoming clear.
Click on the timestamp in the
description if you'd like to skip this
intro. My name is Kaungle. I'm a
Torontonian filmmaker with a background
in mathematical physics dedicated to the
explication of the variegated terrain of
theories of everything from a
theoretical physics perspective, but as
well as analyzing consciousness and
seeing its potential connection to
fundamental reality, whatever that is.
Essentially, this channel is dedicated
to exploring the unerived nature of
reality, the constitutional laws that
govern it, provided those laws exist at
all and are even knowable to us. If you
enjoy witnessing and engaging with
others on the topics of psychology,
consciousness, physics, etc. the
channel's themes, then do consider going
to the Discord and the subreddit which
are linked in the description. There's
also a link to the Patreon that is
patreon.com/kurtjongle
if you'd like to support this podcast as
the patrons and the sponsors are the
only reasons that I'm able to have
podcasts of this quality and this depth
given that I can do this now full-time
thanks to both the patrons and the
sponsors support. Speaking of sponsors,
there are two. The first sponsor is
Brilliant. During the winter break, I
decided to brush up on some of the
fundamentals of physics, particularly
with regard to information theory, as
I'd like to interview Chiara Marto on
constructor theory, which is heavily
based in information theory. Now,
information theory is predicated on
entropy. At least there's a fundamental
formula for entropy. So, I ended up
taking the brilliant course. I
challenged myself to do one lesson per
day, and I took the courses random
variable distributions and knowledge/
uncertainty. What I loved is that
despite knowing the formula for entropy,
which is essentially hammered into you
as an undergraduate, it seems like it
comes down from the sky arbitrarily. And
with Brilliant, for the first time, I
was able to see how the formula for
entropy, which you're seeing right now,
is actually extremely natural. And it'd
be strange to define it in any other
manner. There are plenty of courses and
you can even learn group theory, which
is what's being referenced when you hear
that the standard model is predicated on
U1 cross SU2 cross SU3. Those are league
groups, continuous league groups. Visit
brilliant.org/ org/toe
to get 20% off an annual subscription
and I recommend that you don't stop
before four lessons. I think you'll be
greatly surprised at the ease at which
you can now comprehend subjects you
previously had a difficult time groing.
The second sponsor is Algo. Now ALGO is
an end-to-end supply chain optimization
software company with software that
helps business users optimize sales and
operations planning to avoid stockouts,
reduce return and inventory writedowns
while reducing inventory investment.
It's a supply chain AI that drives smart
ROI headed by Amjad Hussein who's been a
huge supporter of this podcast since
near its inception. In fact, Amjad has
his own podcast on AI and consciousness
and business growth. And if you'd like
to support the Toe podcast, then visit
the link in the description to see
Amjad's podcast because subscribing to
him or at least visiting supports the
toe podcast indirectly. Thank you and
enjoy. Let's do an introduction once
more. So, what is the free energy
principle specifically? specifically its
relationship to a theory of everything
as that's what this channel is about,
right? Um
so my usual response here is do you want
the the high road or the or the or the
low road? Um let's take the high road.
Uh given that we're talking about
theories of everything. Um so the free
energy principle is a principle of least
action. So it's a method really. It's
put most simply a method that allows you
to identify the most likely dynamics,
the most likely way a process will
unfold. What are the what is the process
that we're talking about here? Um well,
we're talking about things like you and
me, particles or people. Um so the first
thing to note is that you can um apply
standard variational principles of least
action to any system specifically a
random dynamical system of the kind that
could be described by say a launch
equation that underwrites most of the
physics we know. But the special thing
about the free energy principle is it
tries to understand the relationship of
something in relation to everything
else. So you're starting from the
premise that something exists and then
you have to think carefully your what is
a thing and how do I distinguish it from
something else. So immediately you start
you have to introduce a partition
between the states of things um that
comprise states that are internal to the
thing and states that are outside the
thing and thereby in think carefully
about how those states are coupled. And
what happens is that you have to
introduce a further set of states known
as blanket states that constitute a
markoff blanket that uh mediate a
birectional exchange between the
internal states and the external states.
So you've got this um notion now of
taking the states of any universe, any
system that you want to try and
understand and partitioning it or
carving it into four subsets. internal,
external and then sensory and active
states that constitute the blanket
states where the active states mediate
the effects of the internal on the
external, the inside on the outside and
the sensory states conversely mediate
the influences of the external on the
internal. So with this particular
partition which you wouldn't need if you
wanted to now just move on and develop
um say quantum mechanics or statistical
mechanics or language in classical
mechanics. We're now in the special case
of dealing with a system that has this
partition. And in this special case,
those conventional variational
principles of least action
translate into or um can be used to
associate the paths of least action, the
most likely paths that the system will
take, particularly the states of the
particle or person that we're talking
about. um we can associate those paths
of least action with paths that minimize
something called variational free
energy. Uh so that's basically it. And
then the story is well what's what's
variational free energy? Well,
variational free energy uh is as with
all actions in physics, it's just a um a
path integral or a time integral, a sum,
an accumulation of uh a functional
usually known as a lronian um where in
this instance the fun the functional in
question, this variational free energy
um can be read as exactly the same
quantity that statisticians
um
psychologists,
people trying to understand data would
treat as a proxy for the evidence for
some model of the world. So this is
known as basin model evidence. Um
statistically it's also known as a
marginal likelihood. the likelihood of
these sensory data the sensory the path
through the sensory states under a
particular model that would try to
explain a hypothesis that would try to
explain those data. So you've got this
interpretation or certainly the fact
that the functional form of this
variational free energy that is being
minimized by the passive least action of
the autonomous the active and the
internal states of something a particle
or a person now looks as if it is trying
to minimize a quantity which provides an
approximation or a negative uh
approximation to marginal likelihood or
model evidencing. So in other words, it
looks as if the most likely paths are
trying to maximize model evidence. So
one can read that in many different
ways. can read that. Um and um as Jakob
Howi has read it, uh a philosopher and
neuroscientist who um uh has a a
commitment and understanding to this
kind of formulation as self-evidencing,
literally interacting with your
environment, actively inferring,
engaging with your experienced world,
your eco niche in a way that looks as if
you're trying to solicit the most
evidence. evidence for your model of
that world. This quantity is also found
in machine learning. It's known as an
evidence lower bound. I should um
qualify or just clarify that in machine
learning this free energy is the reverse
of the free energy used in physics. So
in machine learning they try to maximize
the negative free energy um aka an
evidence lower bound or elbow. um while
in physics you're you're always
articulating in terms of minimizing a
potential energy or minimizing in this
instance some variation free energy. So
you'll find that uh exactly that the
same functional the same quantities the
same measure of the goodness of some
model of how you think your sensations
your sensorium was generated um in terms
of um the you know this um variational
free energy that leads you to an
interpretation of
people particle persons inferring,
accumulating evidence, making inferences
about the states of the world that are
generating their sensations. So that in
a nutshell, or perhaps not a nutshell,
is is a sort of formal explanation of
the free energy principle. I did sort of
slip in at the beginning very much like
um things which you you may be familiar
with when you were at school. uh say
Hamilton's principle of um spatial
reaction
um it is
just a method you know it allows you um
to identify predict simulate engineer
those trajectories those paths those
dynamics those processes um that will um
minimize the this this action functional
or the path integral of the variation of
free energy. So what that means is that
if you now understand um or have at hand
the functional form of your variational
free energy that depends upon posterior
beliefs or beliefs about the outside
world under a generative model quite
simply a probability density over the
external causes of the consequences that
are the sensory states. Um then you can
use that methodology, use that principle
to start to simulate to build sentient
artifacts that behave in the way that we
assume under the free energy principle
that you and I are behaving. Let's see
if I can make a nutshell of the nutshell
for some people who are more familiar
with physics. So let's say you have a
ball. You want to know the dynamics of
the ball. You can understand this with
Newtonian force and that's useful for
certain calculations or you can think of
it as minimizing a lrangeian and then
that actually provides a more useful for
most cases way of calculating the
trajectory of the ball. So then right
there when I said ball we've identified
the ball. Now here you're not just
limiting yourself to balls you're saying
let's say cells instead of talking about
people because we can break it down
simply at least for me for myself I find
it much more easy to think of a cell.
Okay so then we want to know what are
the dynamics of the cell? How's the
cell, a single cell going to act? Okay,
firstly the first step would be
identifying that cell. And when you
mention the word marov blanket, that's a
way of identifying what this object is
because in order to identify what an
object is, it's often useful to identify
what it isn't at the same time, what it
is and isn't. So that marov blanket
delimmits the cell. Now, is that correct
so far? Absolutely. Yeah. So, you know,
I think the cell is a perfect example
here. You got you've got you know a cell
is just defined by the boundary which
would be the surface of the cell and
that would essentially be the sensory
states that I was talking about before
the insize the intracellular states
would be the internal states and then
the mill in which that cell lives which
is usually in in a bunch or a family of
other cells uh will constitute all the
external states. So you've made the very
first step just talking about a cell, a
thing. You've defined it in terms of
this partition into internal, external,
and the uh the sensory states that bound
and separate the inside from the
outside. You may be asking, well, where
have the active states gone? for a cell.
I usually like to associate those with
something called actin filaments that
just lie underneath the surface, the
sensory states and actively push the
cell surface say or the filia um the um
the the mechanisms that cause motion of
the cell should it move around.
So those parts those states that are
responsible for cellular motility. So if
we're now thinking about a moving cell
or a swimming cell for example, then you
need to supplement that partition with
with active states. So that's absolutely
the first step. Um and then you're going
to go on and and now translate the ball.
What's the ball in in this in this
metaphor? You also mentioned the word
birectional earlier. And when I was
learning about this, the way that I like
to understand this was that in computer
science, generally computer scientists
think and can only think in terms of you
have an input, then there's a black box
and you have an output. And that's
essentially computer science in a
nutshell. It's a bit more complicated
than that, but it's in a nutshell. It's
you have an input, you perform some
calculation, and you get an output. The
reason why you said birectional, at
least the way that I understand it, so
please correct this, is it's because of
actions in that model where there's
input, blackbox, output, that's
generally, if we want to use the term
embodied cognition, more on the
cognition side. So you're just this
black box where you're impressed with
sensory information. The input is your
senses. You're sensing all of what's
happening. And then this output now is
the actions that generally a computer
sits there, but we're creatures in this
world. At least we think we're creatures
in a physical world. The black box has a
model. And then one way of maximizing or
showing that your model is correct is by
updating your model or it's by changing
what you've sensed in order to match the
model. Now to change what you've sensed
is to act. So it's useful to think of
two black boxes. So there's one that's
inputting to the other and then the
output goes into the other which is the
external. This is the internal. This is
the cell. it senses and then it acts
upon the world and then that changes the
world which then changes what you sense.
So is that the reason that you said
birectional? Yeah. No, I think that's a
really important observation. Yeah. So
you know before we were talking about
these states that separate the inside
from the outside and I made a big thing
that they comprise sensory and active
states and that there is a a two-way
traffic here. And that two-way traffic
instantiates exactly what you're talking
about, which is a circular causality.
So, you know, I use the word
self-evidencing and described it as um
soliciting evidence for sensory data
that it provides evidence for your model
of what's going on. But in soliciting,
this is something that a computer would
not normally do. a passive or cessile
artifact like a computer, it would not
be in charge of nor would it terribly
worry or indeed be equipped with the
capacity to select the inputs to select
the data say it had to analyze. So just
having a statistical package you give it
some data and it produces an outcome you
say a peak value or some kind of
inference. Um so a lot of computing and
a lot of machine learning you give it
data and it provides a prediction or a
classification.
That's not the kind of computational
process that is implied by the free
energy principle. It's much more as you
put it um inactive. It has you know the
aspirations to provide a mathematical
image of the action perception cycle
where crucially you have to go and
decide what data to base your inferences
on by acting upon the world. So that um
that sort of inactive aspect is the
thing that distinguishes this kind of
formalism, this calculus, this basian
calculus which is quintessentially
inactive. You know it's not just a um
you know a good computer. It can be made
a good computer just by removing active
states if you want to. Um but that you
know that would be a limiting and a
rather um um biohysically unrealizable
and unsustainable kind of artifact. Uh
you know you the whole point here is
that there is a reciprocal exchange with
the world. So your notion of having two
black boxes talking to each other I
think a really nice notion. Um and
indeed when
applying this principle of least action,
the free energy principle to interesting
scenarios,
um one ends up very often um putting two
um sets of uh internal states each
equipped with Markoff blankets talking
to each other. So the active states of
one blanket or one particle or one
person now constitute the sensory states
of the other and vice versa. So you've
got now two systems trying to model each
other. And if their game is to
effectively um provide or solicit the
most evidence for their model of the
rest of the world, which is just another
artifact very much like you who's doing
trying to do exactly the same thing.
What you you what will inevitably emerge
from that joint minimization of free
energy or the maximization of marginal
likelihood is the kind of active
engagement that renders say you and me
as the two black boxes renders us
mutually predictable. So what we will do
is we will come to share the same
generative model the same narrative so
that I can predict exactly what you're
going to say next given that's the kind
of thing that I would say because that's
the sort of world that I'm trying to
model. So immediately you have this um
um picture of the minimization of the
joint uh variation of free energy or the
um the the maximization of the joint
marginal likelihood for shared models.
And one gets from that some quite
compelling and interesting um
formulations of multi- aent games,
communication,
synchronization between uh con specifics
um that all rest upon trying to resolve
uncertainty in the service of securing
actively listing asking questions of the
other blackbox. you asking me questions,
me asking you questions um just so I can
understand what's going on out there
where you are going on out there.
Can any system let's say it's more than
two so in the example that I gave and
that we were talking about there's one
cell and then the external world but
obviously the world is much more complex
than that and let's just imagine it's
slightly more complicated. There's two
cells and then an external world. Is it
always the case that from the
perspective of one cell, you may as well
just treat the external world even
though it comprises an external world
plus another cell out there. Can you
always treat that as its own singular
black box such that we can always
understand the dynamics as two black
boxes or is there ever a need for a
third, a fourth, a fifth? Oh, I I think
I think there probably would be a need
if out there if the external states um
are themselves
um partitioned into things. So if my ex
if my universe
is um composed of external states that
can themselves be carved into natural
kinds, you know, like other artifacts
and objects and air, planets, liquids,
uh natural kinds. As soon as you talk
about a natural kind, you're talking
about a kind of thing. As soon as there
is thingness in play, there's a markoff
blanket. So what that tells you is in
principle it would possible to take all
the states that constitute say an eco
niche and this um find identify the
thing of interest say say me and my
internal states and and then I would um
identify my blanket states and then I
got the rest of the states but now I can
start again. I can find another set of
internal states and identify its blanket
states and then take those states off
the table and then start again and
recursively tile all the external
states. So that now I've eliminated
effectively external states and replace
them by the internal and the blanket
states of all other things. And in on
that view what happens is that because
there's a um a statistical insulation or
separation of internal and external
states by the blanket states. That means
I can never see your internal states. I
don't need to know your internal states.
Um because everything that is u knowable
about your internal states is on the
surface on your blanket states. What's
so now the picture that emerges is an
ensemble of things natural kinds um that
are coupled to each other via their
blanket states. None no individual
particle or person or thing um will ever
be have access to the internal states of
anything else. But there will be um
coupling and influences that are
mediated by the blanket states, the
active states um and possibly the
sensory states. Mathematically, you can
actually have the sensory states also
influencing the outside. But for
simplicity, let's let's assume that
sensory states do not influence external
states. Uh it is just the role of active
states to actually couple back to the
outside. You mentioned something
extremely interesting and I want to pick
up on this. You said that the sensory
states can influence the external
states. At least that's not how I
understand it. So how can a sensory
state influence an external state? So I
said that um mathematically it is that
is possible. Um so if you if you think
about um you know from a pure from the
point of view of um um somebody who's
trying to understand the statistical
behavior the probabilistic behavior of a
set of dynamics described as
differential equations or you know
coupled um systems. Um then the the name
of the game really is to ask your what
statistical dependencies that define a
Markoff blanket specifically um a
Markoff blanket renders the internal
states conditionally independent of the
external states given the Markoff
blanket. So that's their role. That's
what that's what is implied by a
separation of the inside from the
outside that all you need to know is the
blanket states because given the blanket
states the inside and the outside are
conditionally independent. Um so the
question now is what kind of sparse
coupling among all the states at hand
give rise to that conditional
independence that definitively specifies
the markoff blanket. It so happens that
all you need is the following rule.
Internal states can only influence
themselves and active states.
external states can only influence
themselves and sensory states. That's
all you need. So with that um condition
in place, you now immediately have a
markoff blanket or a particular
partition. From that follows the
conditional independence and therefore
the interpretation of the um autonomous
dynamics which is a description of the
trajectories or the paths or the
processes taken by the active and the
internal states of a particular of a
particle. Um
so that means that it is actually
mathematically allowable in the sense
that you don't you do not destroy that
uh that markoff blanket or the
statistical properties of that markoff
blanket. It is allowable for the sensory
states to influence uh active states.
And you may be thinking well that's a
bit silly. you know there's no way in
which my photo receptors or my uh you
know my the clear in my ear
materially affect the outside and I
think that's absolutely true. So for
things like you and me um then you would
not normally expect the sensory states
to influence the external states but
that's not the case for much simpler
things. um when um when you look at much
simpler things where most of the
dynamical influences the coupling that
we're talking about that you'd write
down in terms of the differential
equations the longan equation um most of
those influences are basically short
range so you know we can preclude action
at a distance for example if you're a
single cell you know unless you're next
to me I don't really know what you're up
do I'm having to exclude here all sorts
of interesting things about long range
electrochemical communication and
electrical gradients and the like but
let's just take um a bag of cells um
that um that just diffuse stuff locally
they just they touch each other and
that's the only way that they can they
can influence each other is by um being
proximate in some ukidian space so
everything's short range now in this
situation you have a very different kind
structure. So here the cell the sensory
states are the cell surface and when
these active states that lie underneath
the cell surface c change the
environment they do so by pushing the
cell surface into the external mill and
cause changes in the sensory states the
surface states of other cells. So being
a cell is probably a good example of
where your sensory states which just are
your surface states um actually do all
the heavy lifting in terms of changing
the outside the spatial uh spatial
relationship with all the other cells
that you're co-inhabiting a particular
organ uh for example. So um you know
it's a little bit counterintuitive um
but I think a really interesting um sort
of you know um thought experiment um and
actually a practical uh consideration
when it comes to looking at the
different ways in which um insides
coupled to outsides and the nature of
interactions between the internal states
of something and the external states of
something. Um, and we sort of take it
for granted that we can do action at a
distance, you know, uh, literally I can
talk to you in in Canada while you're
talking while I'm in London. Um, you
know, that that is that that is a a
beautiful example of this action to
distance. Um that means that you we have
quite a special um kind of coupling
between our sensory states and our
active states. That is not um um a gift
um of very simple um cellular like
structures or automter that that can't
interpret signals um or be subject to or
be sensitive to um influences uh at a
distance. Just so you know, or for
people who are listening and if this
wasn't obvious enough, the free energy
principle is famous for or perhaps
infamous for being somewhat inscrutable.
For people who have a physics background
or math background, what would be the
minimum prerequisites? This is how I
like to conceptualize the podcast.
Before I interview someone, I think
about okay, what are all the pieces of
knowledge I need to know prior to
interviewing them. So obvious example is
let's say QFT. You need to understand
classical mechanics, lawrence variance,
quantum mechanics, perhaps bundle theory
if you want to understand Yang Mills and
so on properly. So what would be the
prerequisites for someone to properly
understand the free energy principle?
Let's say if they have a math or physics
background,
it wouldn't be it would be probably much
less than you'd expect to encounter um
at university. I think you'd certainly
need to know um sort of you know the the
basics of variational calculus and it
would be really nice if you understood
where a lronian come came from um and uh
to understand the simplicity of action
you know basically you know exactly
Hamilton's principle of least action and
how that inherits from path integrals of
lrangeians and uh how that arises from
um dynamical systems theory of a very
simple sort where you can write down any
random dynamical system as you know a
stochcastic differential equation or a
lounge van equation um I think that's
probably quite sufficient you know what
um what you would need I think um to
appreciate all the interpretational
richness afforded by what happens to the
paths of least action when you have a
mark off blanket. You need to know a
little bit of probability theory. You
need to know what a conditional
distribution is. You need to know uh the
important you what have an intuition as
to what is meant by model evidence for
example or marginal likelihood. So, you
know, with with I would imagine you a
week's um um foraging on Wikipedia, you
could probably acquire that if you know
if you felt flu if you were fluent
already in sort of um uh in path
integral like formulations of the kind
you can find on Wikipedia. So that you
certainly wouldn't need know what sort
of bundles were. You wouldn't need
category theory. You wouldn't need to
know anything about gauge theories. um
you you know you wouldn't even you
wouldn't even know need to know about
lrange multipliers you yeah but you need
to know um you know uh the basics of how
to uh how how to understand um
differential equations with you know
with random fluctuations with a
probabilistic or stochastic aspect to
them and how you can understand paths of
least action uh in these kinds of
systems your example of Wikipedia is is
on point because the way that I
conceptualized this interview, this
podcast, and the way that we spoke about
it prior to going on air via emails is
it's going to be tendike or gossamer
like where you have these words
imagining what you're saying is like a
Wikipedia page and you say certain
keywords which would be if you were a
Wikipedia page underlined in blue and
worthy of their own investigation in and
of themselves. So, some of these I'm
going to pick out and interrupt you
sometimes. And I apologize for that like
I did earlier in order to
in order to properly set the
prerequisites because we had a 4hour
behemoth before and that was meant to
serve as an introduction to the free
energy principle. However, there were
some people who were still uncertain as
to exactly what the free energy
principle is. So, this will serve as an
introduction to that introduction. Okay.
You mentioned marginal likelihood
evidencing and I believe you see those
two as the same and I'm unclear as to
what any of those two are. So can you
give an explanation what is model
evidencing marginal likelihood?
Ex excellent question. So this is where
you you would need to be slightly fluent
um in the the concepts and constructs
that statisticians um would bring to the
table. So um if I now um want to use
probability theory um to articulate the
um the the job of a statistician um
trying to make sense of data. Um and
just note that that sense making is
basically the interpretation we're
putting on these paths of least action.
Um then you'd you you'd start off by by
um um understanding the problem in terms
of um estimating under uncertainty sort
of assimilating data whilst um um
quantifying and accommodating
uncertainty due to random effects. So
you know the random effects here can be
read as um the random fluctuations or
the veno fluctuations or the innovations
in some stochastic process from the
point of view of a physicist from the
point of view of statistician
um those that randomness um is inherited
as random effects. Observation noise for
example would be one. If you were
dealing with a state space model, which
is really a model of a dynamical process
that a statistician might use to do data
assimilation given some ev given some
time series data. There may be a
distinction between observation noise or
um um sensor noise and the noise or the
random fluctuations on the states that
can't be directly observed. That would
be known as state noise or system noise
for example.
they both you you're describing the same
thing but from the point of view of
statistician these these the this is
becomes noise or uncertainty or random
effects. So how do you deal with this?
But basically um you're confronted with
a problem of some data and you have a
hypothesis or a model about how those
data were generated by some latent
states sometimes known as hidden states
and hidden um here I think uh just as to
try and connect it to the markoff
blanket they're hidden behind the
markoff blanket so the statistician can
if you can think of that being an
internal states They're surrounded.
They're enshrouded by a Marov blanket.
The data is impressing themselves on
this sensory veil. There's something on
the outside that are latent in the sense
that they're hidden behind this uh this
veil. So they only have access to the
data. They don't know how uh the data
were caused. So for example, they might
have a hypothesis that this drug
treatment
materially affected
um some pathophysiology
that reduced the symptoms that were
measurable or recordable by the doctor.
But it's only the observable data that
the doctor can get from the patients
that the statistician has at hand. Now
the statistician now has to infer was
there a drug effect and what she will do
she will create a a generative model
that um if there was a drug effect of a
certain size then I'd expect a
separation of the data for example now
that generative model um at the end of
the day can always be written down as a
joint probability density
um over the causes and consequences
where the causes is are the latent or
the hidden states that you are trying to
estimate and the consequences of the
observable data that you have at hand.
Given that generative model, you can now
estimate um given some data the most
likely hidden or latent states or causes
of that data. Basically, the treatment
effect that you hypothesize.
So that's the posterior distribution.
That's the probability of some hidden
state say the external states the
markoff blanket given conditioned upon
the data. So that's the holy grail
usually of um a statistical analysis and
and you know what your most classical
inference for example those based on t
tests or f tests um uh right through to
more sophisticated and informed uh log
odd ratios such as base factors. These
are just scoring the evidence for an
effect of interest expressed in this
latent state space um in terms of the
probability of one model relative to
another model. And usually in science
that would be the altered hypothesis
versus a null hypothesis. And then you
can look at the the the ratio of the
likelihood of this model or more
specifically the likelihood of the data
given this model divided by the
likelihood of the data given another
model usually the null hypothesis. So to
come to our example our example of um
you know the statistician trying to um
infer whether the drug has had a
remedial effect or not. what she would
do is compute the probability of her
data with an effect and then compute the
probability of her data if there was no
effect of the drug. So the the data sets
from the treatment and non-treatment
group were treated as from a single
group and then she would use that to
make an inference that there was indeed
an effect. So the that probability the
probability of the data given a
particular model a specific model be it
the alternate hypothesis or the null
hypothesis that's the marginal
likelihood. So why is it called a
marginal likelihood? Well, what you've
done is you've estimated given your
generative model the probability of the
data
having marginalized or averaged away the
thing that you don't know which is the
effect size the treatment effect.
So the probability of the data given a
model is the average probability of the
data given that model and the effect
size averaged under your beliefs about
the effect size. So it that's why it's
called a marginal a marginal likelihood.
Um that's a great question because um
you know it actually um leads one to um
the genesis of variational free energy
on one reading by uh in the context of
Richard Fman's pathological formulation
of quantum electronamics.
He he had this marginalization problem.
Um so he wanted to or one could read the
history as him wanting um to evaluate
the marginal likelihood of um um paths
of say small particles.
um which would necess necessarily
involve um computing or marginalizing
integrating of extremely high
dimensional um probability distributions
which is intractable. Uh so in order to
solve the marginalization or the
integration problem to ensure everything
sums to one effectively to get your
partition function um he introduced um
the variational free energy. And that
was a really clever move because he
converted what was an intractable and
nonrealizable and incomputable
marginalization
uh or integration problem into a
tractable optimization problem simply by
introducing this variational free energy
which was a bound on the marginal
likelihood.
So that's why it's called an elbow or an
evidence lower bound simply because it
now becomes a computable object or
mathematical functional um that you can
evaluate given some data and a
generative model that is always in
machine learning lower than the log of
the marginal likelihood. Uh in my world,
the physics world, it's the other way
around. But let's stick with the machine
learning world. So the negative uh
variation free energy of the physicist
is always smaller than the thing you
want to actually evaluate. So if you
just optimize by pushing up the elbow or
the variation free energy until you
can't make it any larger and under the
assumption that the bound the tightness
of the bound is high, you've now got a
good approximation to what you were
chasing which is the marginal
likelihood. And once the statistician
has that marginal likelihood, she can
repeat the process for another model,
say the null hypothesis with no
treatment effect. And then she can take
the ratio of the free energies, the
variational free energies, and start to
compare the models using base factors
and then go back to the doctor say look
um I am
pretty confident that that drug really
did have an effect. And I can say that
because the evidence in your data
suggests that the marginal likelihood of
a hypothesis or a model that included an
effective drug was 52.6 times greater
than the marginal likelihood if I assume
there had been no uh no change. So
that's where the notion of a marginal
likelihood comes from. Um so the
marginal marginal likelihood just is the
evidence for a model. just is um the um
the probability of some data you in the
present context you know sensory or from
from the point of the free energy
principle the sensory states uh or the
sensory trajectory say time series um um
given a particular model marginalizing
away all your beliefs about the
particular effect size and the
parameters and all all the um quantities
that were responsible for gener
generating those data um um uh you know
um under the structure afforded by by
the model. Is that is that is that
clear? I mean you know these are the
fundaments of um you know machine
learning, data simulation, system
identification uh and and you know um
you could actually argue this is one way
of new nuancing the scientific um
process. not quite in using the rhetoric
of of um Carl Pa but certainly has this
poparian aspect to it that every bit of
scientific inquiry um including the way
we live our lives is just about
hypothesis testing. Um and we just
generate alternative explanations for
the evidence at hand. And then we try to
evaluate the evidence for this
hypothesis relative to that hypothesis.
Evaluate the marginal likelihood of the
data at hand for this hypothesis versus
that hypothesis. This model versus that
model. And then we usually commit to the
model with the greatest evidence. This
just is evidence-based scientific uh
progress. uh and you're having committed
to or selected technically known as
basian model selection uh this
hypothesis you then think about okay
what's the next space of hypothesis or
what's the next portfolio of ideas or
models um that I want to now go and
gather evidence for
I think this analogy is quite nice I'm
glad you've let me down this explanatory
because because a good scientist then
the good one will generate new
hypotheses
and then the problem contending the
scientist who's been who's just chasing
these marginal likelihoods or um model
evidences for her models of of of her
fielding uh of inquiry
is to design a good experiment.
So here we we we we we come back to the
you know the the other side of the coin
that takes us um um beyond machine
learning as a black box sort of you know
give it it some inputs give it an
output. We now come back to the design
of our experiments how we actively
secure and solicit the evidence that
will best disambiguate among our
hypotheses. And I repeat, usually when
you're writing scientific papers, it's a
null hypothesis versus nton hypothesis.
But in real life and in real scientific
thinking, people you normally have eight
hypotheses or 100 hypotheses um um and
they're scoring all of them um um by
evaluating the marginal likelihood of
the data that they have carefully
solicited by uh B optimal experimental
design to maximally disambiguate in
terms of the marginal likelihood of the
model evidence between all of their
hypotheses. So that um that sort of
brings another aspect of um probability
theory to the table um which would be an
important compliment for somebody
wanting to understand basian statistics
the baze aspect of course is is that as
soon as you start to talk about
conditional distributions of the kind
that a marginal likelihood is so it's
conditional in the sense that it's a
probability of some data conditioned
upon on a model or given a model having
marginalized away all the parameters of
of of that model. Um and you're building
a posterior the probability of my um
hidden states the parameters of my model
given the data um falls out of baze
rule. So we're talking about basian
inference here and just straightforward
probability theory uh that can be
articulated in terms in terms of baze
rule. But there's another really
important application of BA rule um
which speaks to this sort of inactive
situated uh statistician where
statistician now is not simply in the
service of the doctor supplying her with
data and asking a a particular question.
Now the statistician is in charge of
designing the perfect experiment that
gives her the data that allows her to
make the most efficient and
statistically powerful um inference
about whether there was a treatment
effect. And that's the um that's the
problem of optimal uh experimental
design. There is an answer to that. is
called the principle of optim bay ba's
optimal design first articulated by
people like um Lindley in the in the
1950s and then rearticulated by people
like David McCain in active learning um
and it is if you like the other side of
the basian coin when it comes to um um
basian assimilation of statistical
assimilation of data and inference. Um,
and one could also argue it's the other
side of the coin when it comes to things
like basing decision theory as well. But
that that's a slight distraction. Uh, I
think we just stick with the big idea
here that you know there are good
look at it like this. If it is a case
that the marginal likelihood is just the
probability of some data given a model
and your job is to evaluate that
quantity and usually optimize the um
optimize the uh the marginal likelihood
or maximize the um the evidence for your
model. You can either change the model
or you can change the data. Um and that
means that you've got sort of two uh two
problems to solve as it were. If you
cast this as an optimality problem as a
maximization of an evidence lower bound
um or a minimization of variation free
energy from a from a finesesque point of
view. Um and that's I think comes back
to your your original uh point about the
sort of two black boxes, two computers
inferring each other. um you know where
there are uh I can either change my mind
about you uh or I can try and change you
by querying you, asking a question,
performing an experiment upon you to get
some better um better data from you that
resolves my uncertainty about you. Is
there a relationship between changing
your evidence versus changing your model
and the psychoanalytic repression? So
repression would be saying you know what
that data doesn't exist let me ignore it
versus the perhaps a cognitive
behavioral therapy technique would be to
say no go out and perhaps update your
model of it view it differently view the
maybe it's our arachnophobia for example
I think it's a beautiful analogy and you
know not probably beyond an analogy
there are people in computational
psychiatry who think exactly like that
um and you know um you can find articles
trends in cognitive science reviews of
the kind you know sort that deal with
you know how do you how do you resolve
cognitive dissonance how do you
understand wishful thinking um so
examples you I think that's a a perfect
example of this way of maximizing the
evidence for your models of the world in
that case it sounds like at least the
colloquial understanding maybe in the
west or maybe throughout the world I'm
unsure is that you should update your
model you shouldn't try to change the
evidence to match your model, you should
update your model. And in fact, there
are some political implications. I'm
sure people shout that on the street
across various political divides. So, is
this an argument to say that updating
the model is actually the one that
should be primary? Because the way that
I understand from how you've explained
it is that both are equally valid.
However, when I look across the world
and I look at how we think just in terms
of common sense psychological advice, at
least to us in the 21st century, it
sounds like you should update your
model. Um but but I think you're right
to say that you know it would be um
disingenuous from a mathematical point
of view to privilege the model versus
the data. Um um
so how does one choose between those
mathematically? How does one I don't I I
don't think you can in the sense you
know you you you can't you can't spit a
coin. A coin has two two sides to it.
You know, um the whole point of this
inactivist um take on sensemaking
um is that it, you know, you you have to
optimally go and listen to the right
kind of news, talk to the right kind of
people um in order to solicit the right
kind of data that's going to maximize
the evidence for your model. Whilst at
the same time, you are updating your
model. um sometimes known as basing
belief updating um um or certain basing
model selection for example. So the two
things go hand in hand. I think one way
of resolving or answering your question
is is just to um say in a political um
um or or um um
perhaps even sort of um um communication
science uh sense or at least sort of the
social aspects of it. Um what you're
what you're saying is that um there is
now once you acknowledge that you also
are in charge of getting the data. Um
then um then you also have to contend
with the problems of how much weight you
afford to that data versus that data and
where you get your data from. Which news
channels do you uh do you um forage?
Who do you listen to? Who do you trust?
Who do you ignore? Um, and we do this
all the time. We do this in a very
skillful way. So, personally, um, in
terms of deploying, um, our attention.
Um so if you're an engineer um and you
were thinking about
assimilating visual information using a
calman filter for example then one of
the most artful challenges or or artful
resolutions that the calman filter
brings to the table is to get the calman
gain right. How much weight do you
afford the prediction errors that supply
the update term of a basin or a calman
filter? Um, and we we do that on the fly
all the time, right down to the level of
um turning on and off the attention or
the precision or the gain um afforded
visual information. So my favorite
example is um psychic eye movements. Um
so just to demonstrate that you could
you know one one can do this experiment
at home. You can just sort of look um
from one side of your visual scene to
the other side and back and forth and
back and forth with sacchadic eye
movements uh and you will not perceive
the world jumping around. However, if
you reproduce the same visual
impressions just by palpating your eye
in the spirit of helmholds. Well, what's
that palpating the eye? What does that
mean? Yeah, if you Well, you can
literally do this now. If you just take
your finger and place it gently on the
outer um aspect of your eyeball and just
gently press in until you see the world
shift around and move around. So you can
see visual motion that is a consequence
of optic flow in introduced in this
instance by you pushing your retina um
translating your retina with the input
fixed. Um, and that is basically exactly
the same from the point of view of the
retina, the back of your eyeball as
moving the eyeball, the back of the
retina with the um with the world
stationary. But notice you only saw
motion of the world when you were moving
your eyeball. When you move your eyes in
the normal way, you don't see that
motion. And the reason is that your
brain ignores visual input during eye
movement. And that's called psychic
suppression. So I think it's a beautiful
example of the fact that every moment we
are selectively ignoring
information that is not newsworthy. We
are selecting it. We don't know we're
doing it, but we're doing it all the
time. Of course, you know, at a much
more abstract and epistemic level,
exactly the same principles apply when
we choose, you know, which newspapers,
which blog, uh, which Twitter accounts
to follow, um, you know, which friends
to talk to, which universities to go to,
um, is it going to be a scholaria or a
Wikipedia, you know, all of these
decisions, you know, that we make in
terms of securing the right kind of
informative, precise data that will um,
literally have a salance in the sense
that it complies with the principles of
optimum basian design in the sense that
it will resolve the most uncertainty
about what I don't know. So this is you
know absolutely crucial this sort of um
um being in charge of the data even
before thinking about the consequences
of your belief updating um you know you
know getting uh just knowing that you
have to listen to the right data and of
course the you know the um you know from
the from a sort of sociopolitical point
of view what we're talking about now is
how to disambiguate between fake news
and true news. how to um um solicit data
um in a way that precludes us being
isolationist or precludes us succumbing
to um cultlike um um ideologies um you
know precludes fundamentalism of a
dysfunctional sort or why is it
dysfunctional? Well, usually because
that kind of fundamentalism does not
speak to and does not um minimize that
joint predictability or that joint free
energy that we were talking about um se
several minutes ago. So what what what
you will find is that um
that dialectic between changing your
mind on the basis of some evidence and
changing the evidence by uh changing
where you look for that evidence that
that balance is at the heart of action
and perception. And indeed you you could
argue that all of action is simply in
the service of gathering better data.
What do you mean by better? those data
that res that minimize your surprise,
minimize your expected surprise or your
uncertainty. Resolving uncertainty about
the way you think the world works and
more particularly how you work in that
in in that world. This sounds like a
deeper issue than just a political
problem. It sounds like an issue for the
process of suggesting that the
conclusions that one has come to was
from a dispassionate assessment of the
evidence. So you hear people say this
generally people who like to think of
themselves as extremely rational people
who've come to their conclusions because
they have objectively analyzed some
situation. It sounds like that is a
doomed project because we're all
sampling different data without
realizing it. Now is that the case or
no? Yes. No, I think that's absolutely
right. Um and I don't think there's
anything bad about it. I mean that
that's just the way things are. So how
does one overcome that? What what do we
do? How is it this the scientific
process seems to work?
Um well it works because um uh the
operational definition of working simply
is maximizing the marginal likelihood.
So but you're at liberty to actually
maximize the marginal likelihood by
either changing the data or changing
changing the model. Um so notice that in
this instance you you're not going to
make any false inferences. you know,
provided that all the data you solicit
is always very consistent with your
model, you you won't need to change your
mind. Um, if you've got the wrong model,
the data will provide disconfirmatory
evidence and and you may well to try and
get data from another source. And if you
can do that and continue engaging until
your model is fit for purpose, what you
have basically done is find a niche for
yourself where your ideology, your
conceptions, your understanding of the
world, the world, the way the world work
is perfectly fine. So you found a
cultural eco niche or possibly a
physiological econ.
Um if you can't, you move to another
one. And so now we have a model of
speciation. Um um we have a model of um
shared narratives, shared uh convictions
that can be communicated. to supply and
teach each other. Um that um is self
assembling and um um self- constructing,
co-created simply because you are
looking for uh at the same time you're
looking for information that resolves
your uncertainty about your models of
how the world works. uh which makes it
look as if from the outside you're
basically changing the world to make
your hypothesis come true and that of
course is just another way of describing
action. So if we come away from the sort
of um the exchange of information as a
scientist or somebody who reads the news
or somebody who's trying to do a PhD or
um um indeed just you know make sense of
recent political events if we can sort
of bring it back down to simple things
like um moving your eyes. Yeah. um
in a sense that is you
changing the data to match your model.
So if you uh so this falls out of the
free energy principle because you know
if it's the case that the autonomous
paths the dynamics that we um um that um
that constitute our our active
engagement with the world. if they're
trying to minimize free energy and we in
this instance minimize free energy as
say prediction error or surprise um
remembering that it's the negative of
the marginal likelihood. If something if
the probability of these data given my
understanding of my construction of the
world at this point in time is very very
low um then it will have a very very
small marginal likelihood or have a very
very high free energy and therefore it
will be surprising given my model of the
world. Some people like to articulate
the you know the that surprise in terms
of a prediction error what I predicted
was going to happen um is nothing like
what I actually sense the data I
actually got. So
imagine how um imagine now you apply
that sort of concept that your the
autonomous states that include the
active states are just in the service of
minimizing prediction error. um how we
would you understand that in terms of
elemental movement and behavior and one
way of understanding that is that
basically your models of say how you're
going to move are actually realized by
creating data that is consistent with
your predictions.
So, I have in my head a a model, a
hypothesis, the notion that I'm going to
raise my arm. And all that's happening
in that um notion is that that's my
belief about state of the world. And I'm
telling my spinal cord and my
musculature and my muscles um that's how
I expect the world to be. And then my
reflexes are driven by the prediction
errors driven uh by the free energy
gradients literally like the ball
rolling down the hill. Um to realize to
change the world so it supplies the kind
of data that I predicted. Uh I just
wanted to mention that um that that
notion of movement
as simply a realization
of predicted
end points,
intentions to move
is physiologically
um fully licensed by things like the
equilibrium point hypothesis in motor
control and motor physiology. But it's m
it goes back even further to um idea
motor theory. So this was in the
Victorian age how people understood uh
movement that basically it was a
physical man manifestation of beliefs
about the way my body should be posed or
what my body should be doing. So that to
me that is if you like an elemental and
quite fundamental example of um the
importance of changing the data not the
model. So if you changed your model in
the context of I'm going to stand up now
and you looked at the data and nothing
is happening, you would immediately
change your mind and say, "Oh, I'm not
standing up." What would that look like?
That would look like Parkinson's
disease. That would be a failure to
properly attenuate the evidence that I'm
not moving when I strongly believe that
I am about to move.
And of course you can understand now the
pathophysiology um the um the uh of
Parkinson's disease
that's due to a failure of um neuronal
message passing and particularly the the
weight or the gain afforded
propreceptive information in that light.
It's a failure of active inference. is a
failure of the active states to um
properly uh respond to um the evidence
um that um or change the evidence at
hand. So this is a lovely example of
ignoring selectively ignoring just like
the psychic suppression with the eyes um
that enables movement. If you didn't do
that, we couldn't move. So what I'm
trying to say is that you know right
from the the inception of these kinds of
this kind of thinking in the inactive
domain uh in terms of ideotive theory
the uh there is a there is I think a
fundamental importance of um your um of
the other side of the coin from changing
your mind which is basically changing
the data uh upon which you make you you
you um
which causes you to change your mind
through through sense making and without
that we wouldn't have action. So you can
almost say that action and perception
are the two sides of the same coin. The
perception is changing your mind by
changing your model to maximize the
marginal likelihood given a particular
model. Action just is changing the data
by acting upon the world to maximize the
marginal likelihood basically maximize
changing the data. So the probability of
the data given the model is so active
inference or that coupling of action
perception is essentially trying to
realize your beliefs about or your
models of your lived world. And if
you're successful in doing that, you've
got the right eco niche, you will have a
high marginal likelihood in from an
evolutionary perspective. You will have
um a um a high adaptive fitness. From a
social perspective, you will be uh
people will listen to you and indeed
your your job in do these podcasts
suggests that you you do indeed solicit
that kind of information uh that causes
people to, you know, to to go to your
channel to attend to your stuff um
simply because they they think they're
going to get good stuff and they're
going to get uncertainty resolving
stuff. Um so this this this I think is
is is is uh puts the balance back on the
uh on getting the data right or the data
data foraging right. Okay. Well perhaps
let me undermine my own credibility
here.
So a few weeks ago and I think about a
year ago or so we talked and I had some
experience about and I was worried and
you said Kurt don't be worried don't I
had some experience where I thought I
heard a voice. It was at a in a
hypnogogic state. So, I was just about
to fall asleep when many people, that
shouldn't be a state that I attribute
much credence to, but I remember being
afraid cuz I heard my wife either say
okay or just some one- syllable word.
And then I was so worried and I worked
myself up into anxiety thinking, do I
have schizophrenia? Oh my gosh, there
was no other voices since then. But I
was extremely anxious. And then you told
me, don't worry. And even Kurt, even if
there is, there's medication and many
people go through psychosis and or
psychotic breaks and so on. But luckily,
I didn't. Luckily, there was nothing
wrong with me. And your words did calm
me. So, thank you for that. However, and
coincidentally, perhaps not, but
coincidentally, a few weeks ago,
I had a strange experience, Carl, and I
wasn't sure if I was going to bring this
up on the podcast for one reason,
because I don't want you to think that
I'm someone who's beset with
psychological issues, but on the other
side, I am driven by a filmmaking adage
says that the more personal the pain,
the more widely applicable it is. And
the opposite is also false. The opposite
is false. So, if you try to speak
generally, you end up speaking to no
one.
What happened a couple weeks ago was I
had this sense and it was so and even to
talk about it now is a bit frightening.
I had this sense that I was like, "Oh,
shoot. Solopsism is everything in my
head." Just that thought. And I've
because I'm on this podcast and I've
entertained many ideas, it's extremely
taxing to do so because I try to take
different people's points of views
seriously. And perhaps I shouldn't, but
I feel like in order to give them a fair
shake, I need to embody them in some
way, shape, or form. So if they say,
well, all is mind, for example, that's
the idealists. I'm trying to imagine
what would that be like? And if
someone's a materialist, well, what does
it mean that this was dead and it
somehow emerged that we have
consciousness? Either way, the point of
that is to say, I've been feeling like
for almost a year and a half now, just
in a void, not sure what is true and
what's not true. That's fine. I can deal
with that. Except that that led me to
this spiraling of such it was probably
the most terrifying experience I've ever
had in my life. And it took me weeks and
I'm still recovering from it where I
felt like shoot am I all that exists?
And then just that thought alone, I'm
like, I don't want to believe that that
could be the case. And I remember
looking at my wife and thinking, is my
wife even real? How um much of an
imbecile? And how ungrateful and how
foolish is it? And how that that I would
even think that I feel bad that I would
even entertain that thought. Oh my gosh,
I'm scared. I don't want to go to the
hospital cuz I felt like if I was to
truly accept that thought, I could I was
on the brink of just losing it into an
insensate spiral. I became extremely
scared of myself. And I think that
I'm the type of person, I am an anxious
person. And I am the type of person that
tends to obsess over thoughts.
So then I started to obsess over this.
And for the past couple weeks, I was so
scared. So scared of my own mind. So
almost like a hypochondric for mental
disorders where I didn't want to even
look up what the definition of
schizophrenia or psychosis was because I
was afraid that I would see the signs
everywhere. For example, a few days ago
or about a week ago, I remember
generally we all speak to ourselves in
our own heads and sometimes I use the
phrase so I don't like that or I like
that. I use the word I in my own
internal monologue but sometimes the
word yeah you can do this, you can do
this. So sometimes they used I and
sometimes they use you. And I imagine we
all do that. It's colloquially okay to
exchange those two. However, then I
thought, oh shoot, what if I felt
distant from my thought? What if the one
that's saying you is a thought speaking
to me like a schizophrenic may hear? Oh
my gosh. Oh my gosh. I don't want to
hear this. And I was so afraid and I
felt derealized and depersonalized. when
you mentioned Parkinson's earlier that
the difference between the model and
then the data it that didn't strike me
as a a symptom of Parkinson's. The way
you were describing it struck me as a
symptom of derealization.
Anyway, I'm bringing this all up and I
actually feel
good about speaking about it. It somehow
feels
curative to even voice these concerns.
I Well, actually, I don't know. I don't
I don't know why I'm I'm voicing this.
Mainly to mainly Okay, how about this? I
just verbally cascaded incoherently
perhaps. What are your thoughts on what
I just said? The reason I'm saying this
one more time is that people in the
comment section when they view different
theories of what consciousness is, what
reality is? That's the theories of
everything channel in a nutshell. I see
many of them in a similar place where
they feel lost. For example, I've heard
that some people who view Yosha box
ideas that this all an illusion or this
all simulated consciousness, some people
become suicidal. That's actually
extremely terrifying. Luckily, I'm not
suicidal, though. I'm scared that I
could because I've heard that other
people could. I'm not sure if my problem
is just obsessive thoughts or if it was
indicative of something else and I was
so afraid. And it's it's such a scary
feeling, Carl, to be afraid of one's
self, to not even be able to sleep at
night because you're afraid of your own
thoughts and what that may lead to. Does
any of that make sense? And I know that
sounds like it's completely off field.
Perhaps it's not. No, no, no. I think I
think it follows on very gracefully, but
but you've taken it right now to um some
of the most important aspects of of
modeling. um which we all contend with
which of course is is um I mean I
mentioned before you know getting models
for our um um our lived worlds but of
course the most important part when
we're a baby of the world is our body.
So the first thing we have to do is to
build a a model uh of our body and um
work out you know what things that we
are able to move um you know hence motor
babbling and and um the rattling um
probably more important than that of
course is um exchanges with the mother
um and developing a sense that mother is
an object and crucially an object that
is separate from
And that's quite a skillful move and it
takes a lot of mind belief updating and
changing your models and building a
coherent um uh explanation for all your
sensations both the pitic touch or the
all the and the physiological
intraceptive consequences of being
subtled for example and being cared for
um and I'm taking this uh route to the
key thing uh which is basically models
of self and selfhood Um so you know if
if we are um coming back to this picture
of uh some um mathematical universe that
I've now tiled with multiple markoff
blankets encapsulating or defining lots
of particles um and basically we inhabit
a universe that is constituted by things
like us and in initially you know mom
and dad and brothers and sisters and
your um peers at school. Um that means
that our models of our lived or
experienced world have to have models of
other in it. Which means you need to be
able to disambiguate
between sensations caused by others and
sensations that you caused as a
fundamental
um structural aspect of the models
you're going to bring to the table. is
to live in a world which is constituted
by creatures like you. Um that brings
with it you know uh um something quite
special um which
is a model that encompasses selfhood. Uh
so you wouldn't need this if you um were
lived in a world that did not involve an
exchange with other con specifics. Um
but because we do live your our world is
constituted by other things like us we
need to be able to contextualize and
make the inference I did that or you did
that or it's my turn or it's your turn
or you've got that intentional stance
and you know I've got this intentional
stance. So just having as part of the
generative model or the hypothesis you
know the hypothesis that I am me and you
and you is something which characterizes
um one would imagine very high life
forms. Now we go even higher to um
basically philosophers and people like
you. So if you've got if you have if you
spend your life worrying about um the
what is the self? Does the self even
exist?
Well, precisely. Yeah. Well, I mean that
that's that that seems to be the the the
essence of your existential angst and
all its attendant um inceptive and
emotional um consequences. Uh you know,
do I exist? Um and I think really
usefully you brought to uh the table the
notions of depersonalization and
derealization. If this is for physicists
then can you explain to your audience
what those things are because I think
that it it' be really useful for people
that do not know what well to be quite
frank Carl I didn't want to look up this
exact definition because I know that I'm
a validarian and I would just obsess
over myself having these issues. So I
can give an explanation of my experience
and then perhaps you can delineate what
the psychopathology is. Okay, I'll make
an aside first. Some people say that
what we need to do is realize that the
self is an illusion. You can hear this
in the more eastern end. And I know that
many people who watch this channel also
feel like oh they take these people
seriously like I took them seriously.
And I don't know if that's exactly true.
Not whether or not the truth of the self
being an illusion is true but whether or
not that is indeed useful for everyone.
It may not be. It may be at least for me
it was extremely harmful and perhaps
still is and it may be dependent upon
where you are in psychological
development, spiritual development and
sometimes these lessons that are told to
us by philosophers or spiritual gurus or
people seem like spiritual gurus perhaps
they should be taken with such a grain
of salt and I've come to the conclusion
that if it's not life affirming then
perhaps don't follow that perhaps use
that as a clue that that's a
pathological path and don't do anything
that can be drastic. Don't give up. Cuz
I felt like I was in a state where I
could snap and feel like well this is
all a dream. I remember feeling looking
at my arms and feeling like am I even
behind like right now I'm feeling great
and I know it may not seem like it but
I'm speaking with you. I feel safe. I
love my wife. I've actually whatever.
I'm feeling happy right now and I feel
like I would a month ago which is I'm
behind my eyes and this is a person
speaking a week, two weeks ago, three
weeks ago. I was feeling like all of
that could be a model. I could emulate
anyone else's head. I could be anyone
else. This could all be in my head. So
debilitating, destabilizing.
Walking around feeling like, is this a
dream? Constantly checking my fingers
because that's one of the signs you can
check your for lucid dreaming. How many
fingers do you have? And then also
feeling bad like why the heck am I
thinking this is a dream? Shoot. What if
it is a dream? just spiraling,
spiraling, tumbling, tumbling thoughts.
Okay, that's what I had slash still have
to some degree, though not right now. I
wouldn't say that I'm over it because it
was such a recent experience. I'm not
going to say that I've solved it. I feel
like it's tapering off luckily. Anyway,
that's what I had. I would characterize
that as derealization in the sense that
I didn't feel like it was real. I don't
know if it's depersonalization because I
don't know the difference between those
two, nor dissociative identity disorder.
So I don't know those the differences
between those. Well, but it's it's nice
you bring all those three the phenology
is very very closely related. But you
the way you described it I thought was
almost perfect. You know this um um
either um a derealization
um which people normally described uh
describe as they're looking um they are
sensing um something that doesn't quite
seem real. you know, the outside world
seems like it's a movie. It's not it's
not it's lost that tangibility. There's
no um there's no grip that can be
attained that reassures you that that
stuff is actually out there. The other
the converse of course is I'm um I'm no
longer a person. Um and and that could I
think be even more frightening. And both
of these I think speak to um uh speak to
um this dissociation that comes with a
dissolution of selfhood or at least
one's um um um construction of
explanations for the self in a lived
world.
you used a phrase which um I I think was
was quite uh pertinent here which is you
know one should not pursue this kind of
thinking and self-exloration and
introspection unless it is um
affirmatory and and and self-affirmatory
and in a sense that's exactly from the
sort of mathematical and dry perspective
of the free energy principle that just
is maximizing model evidence this is
self-evidencing it is you If you can
affirm through all the right kind of
interactions be the emotional, social,
sexual, u intellectual um that this
you've got the right kind of model of
your world which is constituted by
people like your interviewees and your
wife and all your colleagues. Um then
affir affirming that model simply is
securing um evidence for that good model
of your rich um and incultured world
that just is that that that um that sort
of um affirmatory uh process. However,
there are dangers that you um that lurk
in the shadows which you've clearly
contended with. to do that properly, to
be able to secure the right kind of
evidence that you are um living in a
world of positive um um
constructive, nourishing, enabling human
beings, others, other things like you.
You have to be able to communicate. To
be able to communicate, you actually
have to entertain the idea um that um
there is there is self and other. Um and
simply uh you know to engage in turn
taking you need to have this um this
explicit part of your generative model
um that I am a self.
In so doing, you will also have um
contextualized as part of your
generative model self in a number of
different states. Uh and you need to
have remember before we talking about
the good scientist um having a portfolio
of hypotheses. We're generating a new
set of hypotheses so that we can now
gather evidence of these hypotheses. So
that's part of uh what you are doing. I
mean you're you in in doing these
podcasts you are on um a journey of um
developing different hypotheses about
ways of being. The the danger though
when it comes to different ways of um me
as a self existing is that you can
sometimes um lose entertain the null
hypothesis that I am not a self or I do
not exist in a sentient fashion in a in
the fashion of having particular kinds
of qualitative experiences. This is a
perfectly viable hypothesis. It can be
had in a non-emotional context when you
meet people like philosophers entertain
things like the you know the zombie
hypothesis or brain of vat thought
experiments. These are all really
interesting interesting instances of a
very high order life form thinking about
well what would it be like if I was me
without mehood if I was a zombie what
would it be like if it wasn't actually
me talking what would it be like if
there was no reality it was all just me
all of these alternative ways of being
that speak to selfhood or its negation
or its nihilism um now become plausible
hypotheses for which you have to search
for evidence. And of course, if you are
just doing this in your head and
ruminating, introspecting, there's going
to be very little evidence available to
you to disaffirm
your hypothesis. Perhaps I'm not me. Um,
if you don't actually engage with
somebody else, there is no evidence at
hand for to refute their hypothesis. Uh,
so on the one hand, that is a remarkable
capacity. The very fact you can have
this hypothesis in your head. I am not
me. Uh or it is not me having these
thoughts. It is not me having these
quantitative experiences is quite
remarkable. It's a very very high level
um ability which which I would imagine
where you you and I are the only kinds
of um sentient artifacts in the universe
that can entertain that kind of
counterfactual hypothesis which is
necessary to explore different models.
It's necessary indeed to actually just
behave and have plans. You have to have
counterfactual hypothesis about the
future and different ways of being. Um
but of course it comes with um um it
comes with a price if sometimes you um
entertain a hypothesis for which there
is no evidence on hand that could
possibly refute it. um uh and certainly
if you adopt a particular behavioral
strategy or engagement with the world
that precludes soliciting evidence
against that hypothesis that you are say
you um so examples of that would be um
um things like obsessional compulsive
disorder or agrophobia or um your
rumination disorders um where you
physically um or possibly even
pro-socially
prevent yourself from acquiring any
further information that would allow you
to change your mind. And of course, once
you realize that's a possibility, you um
um you can always you can also get into
the negatively veanced emotional aspects
of entertaining these hypotheses. So if
I've got schizophrenia,
that now offers a very plausible
hypothesis for these dissociative
experiences. Why am I having these
dissociative experiences? Well, one very
plausible hypothesis. I am having I have
a dissociative order or I have
disorganized thought disorder that
characterizes schizophrenia. So, this
now becomes a very plausible hypothesis.
How would you go secure evidence against
that? Um well, it becomes very difficult
because the whole pro point of having
these very high order counterfactual
hypotheses or models at hand to explain
your experienced world. Um is that the
that that they're very that they're very
plausible explanations and it's very
difficult um uh if you have got
schizophrenia, you're not going to be
able to trust any information anyway
because it could be illusion
hallucinatory. So, it's one of these
wonderful um self-fulfilling hypotheses
that are very difficult to uh to
dismantle. Um and you see the same
phenomenology um in in in many
instances. You mentioned behavior
therapy before and in a way that doesn't
have this quite the same horrible
existential angst that you clearly
experienced. You can actually construe
um many phobias for example of the same
kind in the sense that if you are very
frightened of spiders, you're very
unlikely to actually go and solicit the
evidence that would uh that would
confirm the alternate hypothesis that
spiders are not frightening because you
just don't go near spiders. So this is
the kind of hypothesis that maintains
itself because it's undermined
the way that you actively solicit
evidence for your beliefs. But for you,
of course, you you um you know, it's not
a question of being frightened of
spiders. It's a much more existentially
deep and worrisome notion that in fact
you're not you or you're not even a self
um and you're not even perceiving
reality. um that these kinds of
hypotheses that come along qualified by
or associated with um plausible
explanations, I'm going mad um um are
very difficult to refute in the moment,
especially if you if you ruminate on
them. Um they will go away as soon as
you start re-engaging with with other
people. That's what I found to be the
case, Carl, is that the more I talk
about it, the more I'm speaking with
you, the speaking with people and not
being so in my head almost
instantaneously, it starts to dissipate.
And also, just so you know, there's a
danger for the people who watch this
channel that it's seen as a spiritual
triumphant state to be egoless, to have
ego death. So then, just so you know,
when I was feeling that, I was then
telling myself, but am I supposed to
have ego death? Is this what ego death
is like? And now I feel bad. Am I just
not strong enough as a person? Which
then I feel like I'm less on the social
hierarchy because I'm just a coward who
cannot deal with
who isn't psychologically strong enough
to deal with potential ego death. If
that was even ego death. So that those
are there's so many dangers in this and
I didn't realize this. I had this
insight in that episode or experience
that Kurt Curt Kurt something was like I
was talking to myself or something was
talking to me and telling me Kurt you've
been thinking way too much. This is
you're extremely analytical. I never
would have thought of myself as someone
who's too analytical before. It was
clear to me that I was too analytical.
And there's nothing wrong with being
analytical. There's nothing wrong with
thinking. But you've been thinking a bit
too much. Feel more. Just ground
yourself here. Engage in this world
more.
And and there was also this feeling that
I don't love myself, which is a strange
feeling, Carl, that I don't have that
I'm a bit hard on myself. And I would
have never said that before. I would
have thought I'm not hard enough. I need
to study harder. I need to prepare for
these podcast harder. I need to release
more. I need to learn more. Push, push,
push, push. It was only then that I felt
like Kurt that's been dangerous, man.
Like just relax and and don't worry too
much and feeling deep talking about this
somewhat publicly is a bit embarrassing
because I do feel like by saying this
like there's still that part of me that
feels like am I saying this to give my
way out because I'm truly lazy and I
want to say this. So I get the sympathy
of for example you maybe the audience to
say Kurt no no no you're doing great. So
then I can get I can feel there's so
much self-analyzing that's going on
right here Carl.
Anyway I felt like Kurt you were
thinking too much. Just relax perhaps.
Don't engage as deeply as you have been
with these ideas. Don't entertain them
as much. You maybe you're in a fragile
state right now. You could do that
later. Right now take it back. That's
what came over me. And also this lesson
that I don't have enough self-love or
self-acceptance. Last night I looked up
I was using a rubber band for my
thoughts like self-administered aversive
conditioning when you snap yourself if
you're performing a bad habit. So I
thought maybe I could do that with my
thoughts. So anytime that I feel like
that that would encourage my mind to not
feel like that. I looked it up and it
said that works for physical habits but
not for mental habits. So stop that. And
what works is ACT I believe acceptance
and commitment therapy which is a CBT
technique. So then last night I was
telling myself, you know what? Try that
out. Accept these thoughts. Now I'm not
exactly sure what it means to accept
them. I don't precisely think it means
entertain them, but at least meet them
not with horror and dread and avoidance,
but just say that's okay, man. You think
like that. Some people feel like that
sometimes. So I started doing that. And
last night was the first time in the 3
weeks since I've had this that I felt
absolutely like my regular self. Almost
from 5 minutes of this quote unquote
acceptance therapy. And then I woke up
this morning felt like my regular self.
Like I'm behind my eyes. I have a I'm in
this world. That was fascinating. Okay.
So I said quite a few statements right
there. I'm sure there's plenty you want
to comment on. What I'm also interested
in for you to put a pin in your hat is
what the heck does this self-acceptance,
self-love, if that's even the same, mean
in terms of the free energy principle.
Okay, so I've basically just poured
myself out there.
There you go. Sorry, Carl, for you to
pick up all those pieces. I know it's a
huge responsibility. I trust you. You're
someone who studies this. You're
extremely extremely bright and you have
such a wealth of knowledge and I do feel
like what I'm going through is not
something terribly unique. I do feel
like this is something that many people
who are on this journey of understanding
the world and consciousness and their
place go through this perhaps at some
point. And I think I was trying to
emphasize that by saying that you know
it is a gift that you're able to have
these existential crises. Um you know
there are dangers that lurk which you've
clearly encountered but at the end of
the day the very fact that you can
entertain these counterfactuals
is you know quite remarkable. You know,
to my mind, it's it would be the highest
expression of the human condition just
to consider we those alternative
hypotheses where bits of our humanity
are just not there anymore or have a a
different disposition or relationship to
reality or indeed other people. There
are lots of things you said made made a
lot of sense from simple things like you
know soliciting reassurance from others
that you don't have to do um any more
work in terms of preparing yourself and
being a good a good u expounder of ideas
or or or interviewer or bookw writer or
or or whatever. Uh you know that's
exactly what you should be doing. That's
that's exactly securing evidence for
yourself models of an affirmatory sort.
Uh and the more you do that then the
more uh the more that model will be fit
for purpose and you will have the the
right kind of marginal maximizing your
marginal likelihood. But you're in a
difficult position because your job is
actually to explore other ways of making
sense of things and other ways of
thinking things. So you're you're
compelled to explore alternative
hypotheses. Um and you know you you've
described um the you know the potential
um nihilism and um um that I presume
quite nightmarish um I can't now
remember night nightmares but I'm I
imagine that all of us do go through
this when we have nightmares as
children. I think you stop having true
nightmares in your 30s and 40s. But uh
you know the that sort of you know
before you've really got that grip and
maintain that grip on selfhood and you
in your in your lived uh in your lived
world as part of that and engage with
that world before you've got there. you
know, it must be absolutely awful, you
know, nihilistic to to occasionally lose
that and then, you know, worrying that
you're never going to get it back. Does
remind me of certain um certain um drug
induced states. You know, I I can
imagine that you're the kind of person
who will be very afraid of having a very
bad trip. Um and I think very frightened
of having one. Yeah. Yes. That that is
correct. And luckily I wasn't well what
I imagined what I was going through
would feels like how someone would feel
on a on a terrible psychedelic trip.
Yes. Um and it's interesting you bring
up psychedelics because of course you
know um there is a move um in sort of
pharmacologically assisted talking
therapies you know to to to use
psychedelics simply um not to aspire to
u I I don't know what ego death means
but I I can have a guess at it from the
point of view of meditation and
mindfulness um but there's a really
interesting connection between um the
use of psyched elics um and the
aspiration of many um meditationike
practices um that would I think subsume
the intent internal attention states um
of um of meditation and your current uh
practices of mindfulness which is really
to try and redirect your attention to
the sensorium and usually the
interceptive part so it's it's like
breathing for example so this is the
exact opposite of what you've been
It's exactly
deploying that attention all that um um
game control we're talking about in
terms of selecting what kind of
information sensory information sensory
states to um engage and um determine
your belief updating. So putting it
putting all that attention out to the
sensory side of your deep hierarchal
models, your your constructs. Uh what
you've doing is the opposite. You've you
you've been actually wandering around at
the deeper the highest levels of these
hierarchal models that Sorry. So in back
when we were initially talking I said
there's a black box the input output and
then there are two black boxes. It's as
if you're saying pay attention to the
sensory. Forget about the action. We
haven't talked much about the action,
though obviously as in body creatures,
sensory and action are tied. It's as if
what I've been doing was staying within
the box and creating my little
sensations and actions within there as
little loops. And you're saying pay
attention to the senses that come from
the outside. Is that what you're saying?
Or Yes. Well, I'm not saying you should
do you you will do um everything uh in
the right way under the free energy
principle. What I'm saying is that the
what I'm just saying is that the the
skilled practitioners of mindfulness and
meditation I would imagine of the kind
that would lead to ego death or I'm not
quite sure what that means. Um it um uh
w would
employ exactly the same kind of
internally mediated and sometimes if
you're very skilled valitionally called
forth mechanisms um that are actually um
targeted by psychedelics there
that require you now to do all your
belief updating and evidence
assimilation and sense
at the much more the input level of of
the black box not at the if you like the
highest level which you could think of
as an output in terms of selecting the
plans or what am I going to do next and
what kind of person am I narratives that
we give ourselves that contextualize the
way that we behave and the other things
that we do um so you know I think there
mechanistically a really interesting
connection between the notion of you
ruminating going in circles around your
head exploring every darker and darker
um uh um corners of your mind and
different hypotheses for which there's
very little evidence available simply
because you're not attending to the
sensorium. You're not talking to
anybody. Yeah. You're not for example,
you're not you're not focusing on your
breathing and indeed you try and
supplement that with an elastic band
just to get yourself back to the sensor.
That's interesting. certainly. So, um I
I think that you know you might you may
well guess you probably are um skilled
in meditation. Um but that kind I think
the objective of um becoming a skilled
practitioner of mindfulness or
meditation is simply to get some
valitional control over that sort of
attention um that is paid to these
deeper machinations versus attention
that is paid to the sensorium that
underwrites the psychedelic aspect. the
um the allure of just sensory uh
patterns and um um the sensations
um and textures that you get, you know,
when when taking psychedelics. So, you
know, getting control of the balance um
um so it's not the fact you're attending
to your breathing which is important.
It's the fact that you can valitionally
redirect your attention away from
selfhood
control of it. So, but you seem to have
got control um by this acceptance. And
it strikes me that, you know, in the
absence of um feelings of an emotional
sort that were articulated in your
description in terms of, you know, I'm
an awful person. I'm not fit for
purpose. You know, I'm not well
prepared. Um I um I'm not able to man up
and own this ego uh ego death. uh all of
these sort of personal but quite
emotional constructs effective veilanced
um aspects they are also hypotheses
they're also explanations so the idea is
that you know anything that you can talk
about has to be part of an explanation
for particular ways of being that you
know I can be a worthless person or in
this sense I am a worthless person I'm
not a worthless person uh you know and
you since I I'm in a state of anxiety
I'm not in a state of anxiety we have to
recognize when we are anxious. Anxious
is just a state of being um which is
necessarily called for in certain
situations and rebalance this
attentional precision waiting in um in
computational psychiatry. Um
to make your belief updating fit for
purpose in this partic in this
particular context. Um, what I'm trying
to get to is why acceptance might have
worked. Because I imagine that if you
were suddenly found yourself ruminating
and locked into those ruminations,
um, then very much akin to someone on a
bad trip who thinks, "Ah, I am going to
be locked in this forever. This is going
to be my uncertain state of being for
eternity because there is no reality
today." That's how it feels. Very how
felt. Yeah.
that um that feeling will well if that
is true I must be feeling anxious. You
are then going to look for evidence that
you're feeling anxious. uh um and
because you are anxious uh you will
experience certain cardiac acceleration
certain uh intraceptive um flight or
fright like responses
that will supply evidence that you are
anxious and then that becomes evidence
yes I am right I am now in a state of
nihilism I do not exist and I should be
anxious about that and yes I am anxious
so you get into a um a vicious circle.
So this is a sort of uh good
oldfashioned cognitive behavioral
explanation for things like panic
attacks that you know uh you quite
reasonably in in an entirely basoptal
way make sense of intraceptive bodily
gut feelings literally um you make sense
of them with the hypothesis ah I must be
in an anxious state of being and that
conclusion that hypothesis then
generates autonomic actions that are
realized reflexively in the way we
talked about um when we're looking at
the Parkinson's idea um and that will be
reflected in terms of cardiac
acceleration uh neuroendocrine releases
uh into your body and your body will
change and your body will supply signals
interceptive evidence yes I am anxious
so it's again a self-fulfilling prophecy
in exactly the same way the idea theory
means that raising my hand is just uh a
realization of my beliefs but I can
literally raise my levels of anxiety in
exactly the same way but invisibly from
the outside but not when I can sense my
own body. So if you got yourself caught
up into this joint hypothesis,
I am in a nihilistic existential state
and I should be really worried about
this and anxious about this. Then it is
quite understandable that you are going
to use signals of anxiety and angst
generated by your body as evidence that
yes, I am now um divorced from reality.
I'm an person. I am, you know, in a in a
dark and nihilistic um um place and
there could be no other place. There
could be no reality.
That's a hypothesis.
If you can just wait for the evidence
that that hypothesis is incorrect simply
by letting your body calm down so there
is no further evidence of any anxiety.
Then you can find secure even from your
own body, even without talking to
somebody. You can secure evidence. Ah,
the hypothesis that I am in a state of
internal nilism and anxiety is a silly
hypothesis because the evidence refutes
it. I can now feel my you not possibly
personally but you you will synthesize
all your interceptive feelings um in a
way that um provides evidence against
the fact that now I am a deeply
nihilistic um anxious state. I think
that just is the motivation for the
acceptance. It is pushing through to get
to a state of mind and a state of body
literally you know realizing your good
and making sense of your gut feelings so
that you can now refute the joint
hypothesis that I am uh in a state of
nihilism and I should be jolly
frightened about this because there's no
evidence that you're frightened anymore.
So this was just a piece of um um
hypothesis building of you know a very
sophisticated and um uh uh and
philosophical sort you know the highest
level of exploring alternative ways of
relating to the world. you now have I
think a very useful insight um into what
into the gift of retaining selfhood that
we I think we all we all take it for
granted but it's a quite a fragile thing
you know uh luckily um you know most of
us get through the day if not hopefully
uh most of our lives you know by
retaining that grip and just you know
continue securing evidence that this is
the right hypothesis I'm a person I am
me I am functional. This is, you know,
this is the way I'm meant to be and
these are the kinds of things I do and
the kinds of people I talk to. But that
is such a fragile self assembled and has
to be maintained hypothesis that you
don't that you that fragility I think
only is revealed occasionally and only
to some people when they have the
alternative hypothesis that you know I
I'm not me or you know me is not quite
as functional as I thought I was or I'm
several me or me uh um me uh I am only
me and there is no reality out there.
How is it that you prevent yourself from
getting into existential crisis when it
seems at least to me from the outside
that you study similar not theories per
se but the free energy principle is
about existence and is about selfhood.
So, is your model so strong, Carl? Is
your model already so strong that you
can entertain these without worry that
you'll break yours or without that being
a potential possibility? Or is it
because you purposefully analyze it
dispassionately, analytically,
intellectually, so that you're not
identifying with what you are writing
down on a piece of paper? How is it that
you prevent yourself? Or is it
constitutional, like by predelection, by
personality? You're not neurotic. You're
not as neurotic as I am. Um, I I think
there's there's probably truth to all
that. And um and by being neurotic um
you know that's an entirely your
neurosis are absolutely essential to get
through life. Um you know I have a
particular set of of neurosis um which
you know I treasure and try to and try
to I in the big five model. Yes. Um um
but I think you're also right that um
some people might call this mentalizing.
I think what you were doing is that you
were um in a
raw enthusiastic and creative way were
just exploring different hypotheses
about the way that you yourself should
it exist um um relates to um you the
rest of your um mind and and the outside
world. But for you it got conflated with
um uh emotional states like anxiety um
um and and your self-worth and and those
evaluative uh states of being. Um so if
you want to in your words be more
dispassionate about this kind of mental
exploration on the inside then you have
to um you you have to train yourself not
to conflate the two. One way of doing
that is just to become to mentalize. So
the mentalizing is usually taken as a
way of if you like um disentangling what
we what we would normally quite
functionally put together certain states
of being um of a sort of um intellectual
sort or indeed a physical sort uh or
just a contextual sort usually come
along with some uh emotional veilanced
effective um um uh aspect simply because
that's the way the world is. So if
you're say um um very late at night um
you're normally going to feel fatigued
and slight you know uh slightly less
robust you know in in a way uh in
physically. Now it doesn't have to be
like that but that's the way that
normally the world works and that's the
way that you've learned to model
yourself. Um, if you train to be a
professional, say uh like an airline
pilot trying to land a plane at night or
like a psychiatrist who has to deal with
these um has to see people going through
um these um um
emotional or veanced or effective um
episodes. Whether it's a sort of um
affected in the sense of uh your mania
or depression or whether it's um
the the you know the the comorbidity
associated with psychotic states uh say
schizophffected schizophrenia sorry
schizopffective disorders. What's that?
It's a mixture of um um abnormal mood um
with having psychosis of the kind you'd
associate with schizophrenia. Um so it's
having an emotional aspect to say
delusions and hallucinations for
example. Oh I thought that those so
those don't go hand in hand. So some
people have delusions but they're okay
with it. Yes. Yes. Um, some people have
hallucinations and and would not uh
would not even seek med medical help or
their family and friends would not not
seek medical help. Yeah. So there are
people out there. I guess my point you
know um here is that you can mentalize
it and build professional defenses
against the emotional aspects and I
think that's what I've done. So I think
about these things as a doctor or a
mathematician not as a person.
And if you want uh if you want an honest
answer, the other trick uh is to is is
to uh not use psychedelics, but you
should you should try smoking. So
smoking is is smoking and cups of tea
are great. Smoking what? Cigarettes or I
actually smoke a pipe but cigarettes
will do in an emergency. So there are
certain neurot manipulations and
neurotransmitters. It's the first time a
doctor has recommended smoking. Yes.
Well, I hope we have a select audience
for this. Well, yeah, continue. Could
you finish up your thought? I'm sorry.
No, no, no, no, no. You were saying the
smoking of the pipe does what? Because
I'm not the type of I don't smoke and
nor do I want to smoke, but you were
saying that the smoking does what was
the purpose of the smoking? It's just a
way of using um nuancing your
neurotransmitters that control that
synaptic gain or the gain and the weight
you for different uh different parts of
your um belief updating. So it has the
opposite effect of psychedelics
basically. So that's why people like tea
and you know have a cup of tea calm down
you know stay calm and and carry on or
what is wherever it is nice cup of tea
cigarette and cup of coffee that you
know that that'll sort you out and it's
because all of these um drugs the
caffeine the nicotine they all act on
the same kind of um receptors um at
different levels in your neuronal
hierarchy um that are responsible for
setting that gain control and gating the
attentional and the the attenuation
aspects that we're talking about. So,
it's just a way of getting physical
control over your hierarchal belief
updating. A bit like you're about I
would have thought that the caffeine
would have the opposite effect of
increasing your anxiety.
Not not not necessarily. No. Um you
know, if well, it clearly depends. um if
you're very agitated um um then um that
could certainly be the case. But if
you're if you are worried that you might
be anxious and in fact you're not then
desensitizing certain um certain
interceptive sensations
um that register the fact in fact you're
not terribly your heart isn't pounding
that actually calm you down a little
bit. Uh if it goes too far then beta
blockers will be another nice example of
that's what I used actually. Oh right.
Oh well there you are. So what I'm
trying to say is sometimes the with
skillful use the use of a tobacco pipe
can have the same kind of effects as a
beta blocker.
That's all I would say. All right. All
right. Professor again thank you much
much safer to stick with beta blockers
and you won't get mouth cancer or
anything. So, so if you could I found
the beta blockers work and there's also
some evidence of fear extinction. Have
you heard of that? There's this
professor named Mel Kend who I'm going
to speak to at some point. She takes
people through phobias where she gets
them to be extremely frightened. She
actually makes them almost manic or
panicking at least and then she gives
them a beta blocker and then there they
still feel fear that day. It's only the
next day when there's memory
reconsolidation and the emotional tags
are removed because of the beta blocker.
So you have to have a good night's sleep
and then the fear seems to dissipate
drastically for incurable PTSD. I was
trying to do that to myself. So when I
was feeling some fear, I would take a
beta blocker and then I would feel the
fear less. Still wouldn't be zero. But
then thinking, okay, great. Maybe this
will be like my own intervention of a
fear extinction technique.
Yes, I I was that's very clever idea
actually to combine beta blockers with
what extinction or some people call
flooding. So that yeah so that that's
exactly the kind of way I was um
counseling you you would use people who
smoke use smoking to moderate in the
right some tea yeah there you have it
okay that's very interesting
thank you so much I we'll talk again and
perhaps the next time we speak there
were some questions that I didn't even
get to from Michael Leaven from
Professor Norman Wildberger who's a
mathematician and and there there's
quite a few
Carl, I kept you on for so long and this
has gone well, this didn't I didn't
intend for it to go in this direction,
but I'm extremely glad it has. And maybe
my episode can serve and your advice
episode plus the advice can serve as a
cautionary tale and as well as some
practical advice as to what to do, how
to avoid situations like this when
exploring topics like this. Thank you so
much, professor. I appreciate it. My
pleasure. I look forward to the next
time.
The podcast is now finished. If you'd
like to support conversations like this,
then do consider going to
patreon.com/cur
tj a i m u n g- a l. That is kurtjong.
It's support from the patrons and from
the sponsors that allow me to do this
full-time. Every dollar helps
tremendously. Thank you.